Britain's historic royal palaces, those
no longer lived in by the royal family,
are the backdrop to a thousand years of
British history.
These stones [music] echoed plots and
pageantss, riots and revolutions as
power passed from one generation to
[music] the next. Now, the palaces are
conserved as unique historic monuments,
but they're also the starting point
[music] for adventures, detective
stories that lead back in time. These
buildings are the key to understanding
[music] the lives that filled these
corridors and witnessed events that
changed the world. And unpicking [music]
the secrets turns everyone detective.
>> [music]
>> I'm going to bake his table here.
>> The TUDA kitchens at Hampton Court were
built to serve up to 600 meals at a
sitting to the court of Henry VIII. Food
historians Mark Miltonville and Richard
Fitch are making plans to reawaken the
old kitchen.
>> These kitchens were used famously by
Henry VII, but 200 years of royal
cookery went on here right the way
through the rest of the tutors through
the Stewarts and into the Georgians.
Each year we look at a different period
of cookery that the room was used for.
So it's the same space but moving
backwards and forwards through time.
This year we'll be looking at the early
reign of James I. So around 1600. We're
going to take this empty kitchen laid
out as if the cooks have just left and
see if we can turn it into the early
kitchens of James the First. So, it'll
be filled with 10 cooks, the fires
blazing, the food being prepared, the
meals being cooked each day, every day.
Two meals a day going through the
kitchens. It should be pretty good. And
>> it's a big undertaking.
Another big undertaking has ground to a
halt. In the chapel at Hampton Court,
the royal pew built to give Henry VII a
grandstand view of proceedings below has
a problem. Though the pew's been
dismantled, the problem hasn't been
traced. Lee Proser and his mentor Adrien
Gibson are architectural detectives. And
while the chapel surveyors consider
their next move, Lee and Adrien seize
their chance to take a look.
>> It looks like a great barge.
>> Yes. Yes. There are whole series of
phases built one on top of another here
and our problem is to try and sort out
which comes first and as the whole thing
is collapsing somewhat how on earth to
solve this.
>> I'm particularly interested in the
structural elements of the palace and
the timber work the brick work that kind
of thing. So a chance to come and look
at this was something I couldn't miss
really. The paneling which is all over
this palace hides most of the
interesting fabric if you like. Most of
the woodwork, the plaster work, the
traces of the past have just been
flushed over with paneling. But it's
important in its own right. It's
historic. It's not a good thing just to
take it off for curiosity. So if we get
a chance like this where in an emergency
we have to take paneling off, we've got
to make sure that what we see, which we
will only see for a short period of
time, is recorded properly.
>> There's another joint further along
there. curious.
>> You can look at a building and you can't
quite work it out and you have to apply
your mind to it. When you've examined it
forensically, scientifically after a
while, the whole thing comes together
and the building then begins to yield up
its secrets. It begins to tell a story
and that's one of the most satisfying
things. So, it's like a book that you
can't read straight away, but after a
while, the words begin to make sense.
>> That's why we don't read detective
stories because this is a detective
story. This is what it This is actual
real detective work.
>> Food historians Mark and Richard are
heading north.
>> We're heading up to [music]
Leeds to use the University Library
known as the Brotherton Library and
we're going to use their rare books
collection. It's one of the largest
[music] collections of bookery books in
England. One of the books we looked at
last time we were in Leeds was printed
in 1574 with the pages still stuck
together with the ink. We were the first
people to look at that book since it was
printed in 1574.
>> By starting with those recipes, you have
your your link with the past. And it's
from there that we can start our
recreation. But before that, Richard's
got to take recipes which to the
ordinary man are nonsensical and try and
pick them apart and see [music] if we
can work out what to do.
Try not to skip up the step. Too late.
To discover how the old meals [music]
might have tasted, Richard and Mark are
not only looking for recipes, but also
illustrations of kitchen utensils
[music] so they can unpick exactly how
the meal might have been made.
[music]
>> Because the descriptions are designed
for cooks, they aren't the modern
cookbook. There's no amounts. There's no
timings. How can they time your fire?
Nowadays, we turn the dial up to 180.
You have a fire. I don't know how hot it
is, whether it's windy where you're
cooking. But this means that you have to
start trying to infill all that
knowledge which is missing from the
recipe.
>> That's nice. And so it's working your
way through so many facets of people's
lives. You've got to unpick their lives
to try and recreate their kitchens and
their food.
>> Pickles. That's interesting. underneath
this facia board. Some of these
>> in Hampton Court, Lee and Adrian are
working on a theory that the problem
with the royal pew might stem from
modifications made centuries earlier.
>> It's only when you look so closely at
the wood that you that the timber, which
is all that's left of Henry's holy
closet, begins to tell you the story.
>> Tell you the story. That's right. It
looks as though maybe they've taken out
the early ceiling which was in here
>> to create a new lower floor level.
>> Yes. So the floor has progressively been
lowered and lowered and lowered as the
building's been modified.
>> Okay.
>> And the proof is found in an adjoining
room.
>> We're standing on the late 17th century
floor surface, but we've got an earlier
door, a tuda door, which is has its his
its ground level at knee height.
>> Clearly stopped here. So when we look at
the timbers we've just exposed, the
upper mortises for the lost floor are at
the same height
>> correspond
>> in some ways that helps us to establish
that that perhaps was the first floor
level of Henry's holy day closet.
>> This is this is the piece of evidence
which really clinches the respect level
of it
>> throughout the whole building. Yes,
>> it's the corroborating evidence which is
gradually building the picture of what
this palace was like in the 16th
century. And it it also shows us how
much more is hidden really. You know,
there is lots more of Henry's palace
hidden away um waiting to be discovered.
>> And in the library in Leeds, there's
also been a discovery.
>> First edition.
>> First edition. And someone has written
on some time ago. Very rare.
The library [music] has turned up a very
rare book indeed by the 16th century
chef to Pope Pius V, Bartellos [music]
Scapy. It's an illustrated guide to all
the latest kitchen gadgets from 1570.
[music]
And to Mark and Richard, it's a gold
mine.
You get excited about it because it's
going right back to the starting point.
If it's mixed [music] in a early pottery
bowl with a wooden spoon, cut with an
iron knife. Does all this affect the
final dish? That's what we're looking
at. So, we're as interested in [music]
process as we are the final result.
>> Well, that's what we could do with Yeah,
cuz it looks to me to be a pastry wheel.
Unfortunately, no scale.
>> Nicely made.
>> Cuz that's going to be something that is
going to intrigue people when they see
it and intrigue us to see how it whether
it how it works, where it fits in the
hand.
>> Kensington Palace is best known as the
former home of Princess Diana. The
palace was designed by Sir Christopher
Ren for William and Mary and was also
the childhood home of Queen Victoria.
These days, the palace contains perhaps
the most personal royal collection, the
costumes,
clothes worn by monarchs and courtiers
on state occasions and in private for
over 300 years. With more than 5,000
separate pieces, it's the finest
collection of royal dress in the world.
That is really really
>> though some dresses are on display. The
vast majority are kept in basement
vaults by costume curator Joanna Marsha.
The
>> mantle by Princess Elizabeth. This is
Bunny as it happens. Their dress remains
probably the most tangible evidence of
their tastes, their interests and all
those very personal choices that each
one of them made.
>> Their dress is that most immediate thing
that can survive from them. You've seen
it in images, haven't you?
>> It is very, very personal, and yes, it
is intimate.
>> Joanna and her colleague, Deira Murphy,
are planning to add to the collection,
but exactly what they've got their eye
on must remain cloaked in secrecy.
Apparently,
>> there's a possible acquisition coming up
and I'm going to an auction auction
house this week to have a look at it.
>> And what is this thing?
>> Can't tell you at the moment. I'll let
you know.
>> Is it a hat?
Can't tell you.
>> Is it a dress?
>> Don't know.
>> Nice try though.
>> At Hampton Court, Mark and Richard have
had a delivery.
>> Aha.
>> Right. This should be the pastry knife
from Bartholomeo Scappy's book that we
saw in Leeds. You
>> commissioned someone to make.
>> We've sent the drawings which hopefully
are in here as well.
>> Get into it.
And we have
you get that bit. Yep. There's the
drawing which we hope to be a pastry
wheel and knife. And inside the package,
>> not bad at all.
>> Now we got to find out how this works.
Um well, it's a pastry wheel. We can
tell from Yep. That's fitting into the
fingers as we thought. Ow. Be careful
cuz you'll stab yourself in the hand
with that bit. Turn that way up and roll
it as a past. That's That's all right.
That doesn't stab you. Roll that as a
pastry knife. Or if you turn it round,
you've got a cutter for cutting cutting
pastry
>> way with pies, my
>> And you've got a a cutter for pulling
pastry towards you.
>> So, when was this last seen in the
world?
>> Oh, at best about 500 years ago. At
worst, he never actually made one. He
just did a drawing of one in a book for
you. And this is the first. I don't
know. We Let's test it out and tell if
it's any good.
Joanna and Deerra are heading to the
mysterious auction and secrecy is still
the order of the day.
>> Always a bit nervous with auctions. You
absolutely cannot predict what might
happen. Everyone has their own secret
agenda. We have our own secret agenda.
We have to be very very careful not to
reveal our hand and find everyone else
realizes that this is a premium object
and to us it's going to be very
valuable. Um, so we're just going to
have to keep our fingers crossed and
hope for the best.
>> Well, to help protect your anonymity, we
have the device that MI5 would be proud
of. Bad cam
[music]
right to the right. Thank you.
>> [music]
[music]
>> In the kitchens at Hampton Court, it's
time to discover how the recipes work.
Mark and Richard have assembled a team
who dress in authentic clothing and
[music] for 11 days live the life of a
Steuart cook. They have just spent
[music] their first night in the cold,
old palace.
When we first started, [music] we
thought you don't need any clothes cuz
you're looking at food production. But
we suddenly realized that following the
craft of someone in the past, you need
all of their tools. And their clothes
are part of their tools. They affect the
way that you work. Especially down here,
they keep us warm. When your modern
clothes, nylons and things will let all
your heat out.
And we have a flame.
[music]
And before [music] the team have even
had breakfast, there's an additional
pressure when the panace opens to the
public.
>> It's a necessary pressure and it's a
bonus for us. We could experiment quite
happily with the kitchens closed, but
it's the thousands of people that come
and see us that push us in new
directions. They'll ask a question so
simple that you've never even thought of
that will set the whole team spinning
going, "Ah." It means you have to be the
politest cooks in the world. We've got
to be the only cooks who allow 2,000
people to walk through their kitchen
while they're working.
>> No Gordon Ramsey language.
>> Uh, we have to be a little bit careful.
So, uh, yeah, if you want to say
anything to yourself, go and do it
somewhere else. Warmed up and woken up,
the next task will be to prepare the
great meal of the day.
>> Six stories above, Adrien and Lee are
doing what they like to do best. And
today they're on top of the world.
>> I want to go in the roof on the right
hand side of base court, which should be
one of Cardinal Woolseie's original
roofs.
>> How much of that survives, I'm not sure.
>> A second roof right over in the far
leftand corner.
>> Right,
>> that's part of the palace. It was built
by Henry VII as the great house of
easement. It was the communal lavatory
if you like and ironically it's now
where the chief executive has his
office.
>> But the best thing is the clock that was
installed in 1540 for Henry VI with its
18th century coupella on top. And we can
go right up inside that to look at the
real thing and see if anything remains.
>> See if we've got anything left in there
of the TUDA of the TUDA period or
>> it's all been replaced.
>> That is a fantastic clock. You know it's
one of the great treasures of
>> Hampton Court. Yeah.
>> This is wonderful. Come and look at this
Adrian. Right. What? Oh,
>> yes.
>> This is a
>> That's excellent. This is a wonderful
roof.
>> Hampton Court is one of the greatest
palaces in Europe.
>> And the more we know about that, the
better we can conserve it and preserve
it for future generations. What would
happen if you didn't record a building
and it caught fire and burnt down and
god forbid it would ever happen here
again. But these things do happen in in
stately homes and in historic buildings.
Very often they've never been recorded.
The information is gone. It's lost
forever. We need to record. We need to
collect as much information that about
this building as possible. You wouldn't
think this is 500 years old.
>> No. No.
>> You've got
>> more or less Woolseie's roof intact. If
you go downstairs, there's very little
of Woolseie's brick work of the timber
work of the interiors. Nothing of that
is left. You come up here in the roof
space and you're still in the space that
those TUDA workmen would have known when
they left it as they completed it. It
hasn't changed hardly at all00150
>> at Surbis. The auction is underway.
>> With Joanna and Deedra and Bag Cam in
position, Historic Royal Palace's best
kept secret can at last be told. There
are two items on the shopping list. The
first is a belt.
>> Buckle related to either King George or
King George. I have 200 bill. Back in
Kensington Palace, costume curator
Beatatric Balon has also been doing a
little detective work and she believes
it's a very special belt indeed. In
1788, George III was brought to Q
suffering from what appeared to be
irretrievable madness. Beatatrice
believes the belt was made to
commemorate his return to health a year
later. If she's right, the belts are a
unique part of the story of George III
and the soontobe refurbished Q Palace.
She's hoping to display the belt in
pride of place when the restoration is
complete and the palace reopens to the
public.
>> Can I say 550? 550.
600. I have
650.
>> But as the belt goes over Joanna's 600
limit,
>> she pours out
a very rare piece. I'm sending them
>> bad news for Beatric.
You can see if we're liking them. We
usually do.
>> In the kitchens at Hampton Court, things
aren't working out for [clears throat]
Mark either.
>> My job today is making sauces and I'll
just open the cookbook to make mustard.
That's one of the ones I'm doing. Take
mustard seed and let it soak for the
space of two days. Well, that's that one
stuffed then. So, I'm going to have to
find another sauce. So, sometimes a bit
more planning would have helped, but I'm
sure that happened in the original
kitchen. You looked at Oh, I'll do Ah,
no, I won't. I'll find another mustard.
Excuse me, please.
>> We keep it on there for as long as
possible cuz it nice and slowly, which
means that Ross, who's going to be
turning it, he's going to be sat there
for up to 4 hours. I've just asked him
whether he's got enough water, he'll get
through that really quick. We've got to
keep chopping him up, but that's why I'm
not sitting there because it's a hateful
job to do this.
>> I think it's going to be
>> See you in 3 hours.
>> Yeah. Thank you very much. Pastry wheel.
Time to give it a go, I suppose, and see
whether it does the job. Now, I suppose
is the moment of truth because with the
uh Well, I'm hoping that it Well, I
don't think it's going to cut it. I
think it's going to squidge it together
>> so that it's glued together. So, there
we are. And then
>> Well, I would have might have done that
way, but I reckon
>> that if you
hold it that way,
>> it cuts that off there.
So, that's pretty good.
>> Yeah, it does seem to be, doesn't it?
>> Feels like a lot of work. As the lady
just said, you got to roll it and then
cut it. And I I personally feel it
should do it all in one and then maybe
use the curved edge or the outside edge
for other purposes.
>> Back at Surbis, it's time for the star
lot. This is what Deedra has come for.
The Duke of Windsor's safari suit was
not only worn by the prince, but
designed by him personally. Though now
consigned to the footnotes of history
for giving up the throne to married
divorcee Wally Simpson, the prince was a
hugely popular and dashing [music]
modern figure. He was an icon and an
international trends setter.
>> At £2,000
>> as such a piece of his personally
designed wardrobe is a major part of his
story.
>> Dedra has a budget of £5,000 and not a
penny more. 30,0005
2008 4,000 4,0002
4,000464,08
£5,000
It's at £5,000 now on in the room. It's
at £5,000 and selling now for £5,000.
Thank you very much. 38.
If you want to undress him and then go
and get your boots from
[music]
>> Now all that remains [music] is breaking
the news about the belt. to Beatress.
>> We got one out of the two.
>> You didn't get the belt. Oh no.
Why? Why not?
>> It went above our limit.
>> For what? How much?
>> 650.
>> Oh no. Oh, that's ridiculous.
>> Yeah.
>> You should have got it for 650.
>> I know.
>> Oh, that's so disappointing.
>> I know. I know. It's too bad.
>> All that research for nothing.
>> Yeah. I'm sorry. Oh well.
>> But Beatatrice doesn't give up easily.
She's determined to discover who bought
her precious belt.
>> So they might have gone even higher. I
don't know.
>> In the Hampton Court kitchens, attempts
to recreate the 17th century meal are
being hampered by 21st century
onlookers.
>> Ow.
>> And Mark is getting into hot water.
>> I'm blanching arms.
>> I'm blanching your fingers. I'm
blanching my fingers at the same time.
That's [snorts]
getting better. As long as I get almonds
that I can chop, I can take five minutes
away from talking to three or 4 thousand
people a day and burn my fingers in
peace. Too hot. No, too hot. Still, we
love having this as a live experiment.
There's people everywhere asking us
questions, but every now and then the
balance starts to go. You get so many
people so interested that you go from
cooking to only talking. And we have to
be a bit careful around the middle of
the day not to have too many of us
talking who aren't actually cooking
otherwise there isn't a meal. It is a a
functioning kitchen. That's the
experiment. But it's a functioning
kitchen which is live for the public. It
also has to produce this meal at 3:00
which is something we're very very keen
on this timing aspect. If you don't have
a time frame then you could just fiddle
about all day. And you know what would
the point be? The people that worked in
these kitchens had to get the meal out
on time. So so do we.
I'll show you off.
>> I can't look. It scares me.
>> Going to get the beef off the spoon and
I want it to rest and we'll carve out
that. So, that'll be okay.
>> Just about 2:00 now. So, you got an hour
to go. What's the timing looking like?
Uh,
>> pretty good. Everything as long as I can
get this in in the next 15 minutes.
Yep. There we go. That's
hot food coming through. Hot food coming
through. Excuse me.
>> It's not physically very tiring. We try
and do, as you've noticed, as little
physical work as possible, but it's
mentally very, very tiring. You're
trying to continually pull facts from
the back of your mind forward and put
them present them hopefully
entertainingly and it does really drain
at times.
>> Hampton [music] Court's famous
astronomical clock was made for Henry
VIII in 1540. It was the most elaborate
[music] and complex time piece of its
day, displaying the time, date, and
phases of the moon. As the clock [music]
was made before the published findings
of Capernicus, it shows the sun
revolving around the earth. But exactly
how the clock works and how much of the
original mechanism is still in place, no
one knows. The
>> stairs are quite worn, aren't they?
Aren't
>> they? So some poor devil had to come up
and down to wind the clock. Yeah.
>> Mind your head.
>> Look at this. Very low.
>> Right. Mark your head.
>> It's incredible.
>> Yes. It's not TUDA though, is it?
>> No, it doesn't appear to be from my
quick look at it.
>> I see the hand of Mr. Ren in this.
>> Yes. Yes. [snorts] Oh,
>> he's quite ahead of his time really,
isn't he?
>> Oh, yes. Yes. And clearly that is a 19th
century clock.
>> There's a date on it.
>> 19th century. It looks to be
>> 1879.
>> Right. That's dead right.
>> Here we go.
>> That's great, isn't it?
>> Yeah.
>> The whole place thumps.
>> [laughter]
>> God, it's a real meal, isn't it, when it
happens.
>> Oh, yeah.
It's
>> incredible.
>> Take cover.
>> It's great being up here and that
happens.
>> Oh, yeah.
That is That's all right. You got the
mechanism of the actual clock face.
>> God, that's fantastic.
>> There we are.
>> Oh, look at the date. Ammo 1540 on the
back of that that component. It's picked
out in gold as well.
>> So, we've got the original cogs and
mechanism.
>> Looks like it.
>> Well, that's wonderful, isn't it?
>> Fancy seeing that.
>> Kensington Palace has also been hosting
a little diligent detective work.
>> Thank you. Bye.
>> He's He's brought a
>> Beatric Balon has traced the auction
belt to a London dealer and she's run
him to ground.
>> Beatric doesn't know if the belt's new
owner, Mr. Shepherd will be prepared to
part with his latest acquisition so
soon. Party has a bag.
>> Hello, I'm Beatatrice. Very nice to meet
you. Come in.
>> We'll go this way.
>> I think the effiges they got at um
Westminster Abby.
>> Yeah, it's Well, there he is. You don't
see his good sight. Yeah,
>> you've got a bag with you. [laughter]
One of the reasons we wanted you to come
here is just Sebastian and Caroline
haven't actually seen the bell. They
know it's in quite a bad state, but I
keep telling them it's really, really
nice. And so, one thing would be nice if
they could just have a look at it.
>> Sebastian Edwards is the man with the
money. If Beatrice is to get the belt,
she has to persuade him it's worth
whatever price Mr. Shepherd is now
charging.
In 1789, Britain had [music] perhaps the
strangest celebration in its history.
a national event to celebrate George
III's return from his apparent madness.
Perhaps this belt is the only survivor
of that extraordinary occasion. But will
Sebastian be persuaded this is a crucial
part of the new exhibition or just a
worthless relic?
>> What an amazing survivor, isn't it?
>> What do you think?
>> Can you show me the back?
>> It's rusty.
>> Yeah. Still
>> by its nature will deteriorate.
>> It's fantastic to see it. That's the
amazing that has survived
>> because it's getting to the state where
most people would think is it worth
keeping that but altogether it's a much
more important interesting object.
>> Sebastian is persuaded. Now it's time to
talk business.
>> So have you got any plans for it?
>> Um we were prepared to pay a lot more
money for it than we did. Um the price
of it is £1,600 now which is roughly
what we were to pay for it at the time.
The belt's price has leapt since the
auction, but with the reopening of Q
Palace just months away, a genuine
artifact that recalls the time King
George spent in Q is a must-have item.
>> You see, as you described it, it's a
much more important
>> and Sebastian strikes the deal to the
relief of Beatric.
>> I'm just doing a receipt um for it.
We're going to keep it on approval,
which means we can have a closer look at
it. Yeah, I'm very pleased. I'm very
pleased. It's also I really want to do
some more research. I really want to
find out who wore it. I I might never
find it out, but I I really want to find
out a bit more. So, no. I I feel I can
do a bit more research. So, I think it's
a happy ending.
>> These palaces are more than showcases
and photo opportunities for the public.
They are riddled with detective stories
that tell of power, passion, and the
everyday lives that had their moments in
these buildings.
And solving the [music] clues will
breathe life into ghosts, turning empty
buildings into the story books of the
nation.
[music]
Heat.
Heat. [music]
>> [music]